JON WAYLAND

MS APPLIED MATH | MBA | DATA SCIENCE

CONTACT

(814) 771-1017

jonwayland47@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/jonwayland www.jonwayland.com

St. Augustine, FL

SKILLS

Machine Learning - R, Python

- caret
- ROSE
- tidymodels imblearn
- glmnet
- scikit-learn
- e1071
- TensorFlow
- rpart
- NumPy
- recosystem pandas
- XGBoost
- statsmodels

Data Wrangling

- SQL (SQL Server, DB2, Oracle, Hive)
- Web-Scraping (XML, HTML; rvest)
- Regular Expression (R, Python)

EDUCATION

M.B.A. Entrepreneurship & Analytics **University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign** 2019-2022

M.S. Applied Mathematics Indiana University of Pennsylvania 2012-2014

B.S. Mathematics

Clarion University of Pennsylvania

2008-2012

CERTIFICATIONS

Al Strategy

Cornell University

2023-2024

Data Science Certificate HarvardX on edX

2018-2019

Machine Learning Nanodegree Udacity

2016-2017

PROFILE

Applied Data Science Leader whose team innovates health solutions for under-65 Floridians using machine learning, GenAl, and advanced statistics. Passionate knowledge sharer who evangelizes AI and believes in ethical decision-making. ChatGPT early adopter and super user. Experienced in the fields of healthcare and technology as both a thought leader and practitioner.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Director, Data Science

Sr. Manager, Data Science (Jan. 2021 - Mar. 2023) Sr. Data Scientist (Mar. 2020 - Jan. 2021)

Analytics Consultant (Mar. 2019 - Feb. 2020)

2019-Current Florida Blue

- Grew team of 1 to team of 8 full-time data scientists and engineers
- · Pioneered new program evaluation methodology resulting in decreased difference in matching variables by introducing a custom matching algorithm
- Aligned ML strategy to enterprise needs by maintaining team's priorities with roadmaps, building trust in executives, and setting reliable expectations
- Founded WiseWays, an enterprise ID/Strat system and integrated DB
 - o 150+ clinical users; 150+ analytics users; 15+ ML models; 15+ data sources
 - o Feeds all commercial care management, rewards, member website, Provider Vista (external app.), and Care Connect (internal app.)
- Led end-to-end implementation on 30+ machine learning products
 - Predicted end-of-life for advanced care as an IC leading to \$20M+ savings by persuading stakeholders to use internal model over vendor's model
 - XGBoost model with neural network-derived features (45% precision)
- · Incentivized quick turnarounds with modeling competitions
- · Successfully convinced for multiple in-house solutions over using vendors

Data Scientist

2017-2019 **Availity**

- Increased provider service location accuracy by over 5% by embedding ML model into the PDM product
- Led cross-functional team resulting in segmenting Availity's user population
- · Identified a subset of customers with high likelihood of attrition using registration DOW, slope of transaction volume, and login patterns

Analyst II

Analyst I (Aug. 2014 - Feb. 2016)

WorkPartners | UPMC Health Plan

2014-2017

- Predicted employees with longer return-to-work times after STD claims by combining randomForestSRC, k-means clustering, and logistic regression
- · Led the repeatable integration of nine commonly siloed data sources
- · Contributed to acquisition of HCMS Group through validation of analytics

Part-Time Data Science Roles

2012-2020

- Data Science Mentor | Springboard.com
- Freelancing Data Scientist | Upwork.com
- Data Science Community TA | HarvardX
- Statistical Consultant | IUP Applied Research Lab